This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
Has anybody done the homework and found
the operator
for circular polarization?
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
What What is it?
Yeah.
Right.
Let's um let's just do it quickly.
So, I'll come back to you. Since we
assigned it as homework,
let's just do it quickly.
Um
before
Sure.
1 and -1.
Right?
Right.
Okay, let me just write the other two
cases.
There was the um
There was the
There was the um what what do we call
it? The observable
for the polarization when the
polarization was in the vertical and
horizontal directions,
plus for horizontal, minus for vertical,
and we call that P.
I can't
Why don't people throw these away when
they're no good anymore? I don't know.
Let's try this.
Oh, that's cool.
Okay, there was the um
observable representing polarization in
the vertical and horizontal plane, plus
for horizontal, minus for vertical,
and we call that Oh, boy.
1 -1 0 0.
Uh the X polarization state we labeled
as 1 0.
The Y polarization, the vertical
polarization, we labeled as 0 1.
Okay? So, this is the object which has
eigenvectors X and Y with eigenvalue +1
and -1.
Then, there was the polarization uh the
not the polarization the uh
observable
for the 45° case,
we called these states theta,
and we represented that by cosine theta,
sine theta,
and then there was the orthogonal one,
which was theta plus pi over two,
and that had a column vector, which I
think was sine of theta or
and minus cosine
minus cosine theta, I think, if I
remember.
Yeah, that'll work.
This one is orthogonal to this one. Sine
times cosine minus cosine times sine,
that'll do it.
Well, okay, we're going to talk about
the whether that matters or not. Okay, I
guess we wrote it this way last time. It
doesn't matter, in fact.
And this was
1 1 0 0.
Sorry.
That was for the special case
for the special case of 45°,
and we called that
45°
1 over root 2,
and this one would be
minus 1 over root 2.
This would be this,
this.
And finally, we discussed circular
polarization.
We have started to discuss it. The two
states of circular polarization, again,
you can think of them as two distinct
orthogonal
states. Orthogonal means physically
distinguishable in a single experiment.
And I guess I called that I guess I put
a little
rotation notation like that.
This would be
positively polarized lights, positively
polarized circular polarization,
and the wave function for that or the uh
the
1 over square root of 2,
and you can take it to be 1 i.
Here's the first place where complex
numbers come in,
and the opposite polarization,
same 1 over square root of 2,
1 minus i.
These are
Yes, these are again orthogonal. You can
check that. Remember when you check it
that you should complex conjugate one of
them when you take the inner product,
and then multiply the upper components
and add it to what you get when you
multiply the lower components.
All right, what is the what is the
observable that goes with circular
polarization?
That I don't remember what I called it.
Did it have a name? I guess we can just
put a little
rotation symbol, and that, as was
mentioned a moment ago, is minus i i,
0 0.
We can check
that this observable,
when it acts on the polarization state
on the circularly polarized states,
these are eigenvectors with eigenvalue
+1 and -1, and that you can check for
yourselves. It's very straightforward.
Uh
you just The hardest part of it is
remembering that i squared is minus 1.
All right, now,
where are we? And
what what are we doing relative to what
we did the first day when we studied
classical mechanics?
The first day when we studied classical
mechanics, what we discussed
was the possible states of a very simple
system with a discrete number of states.
The discrete number of states could have
been two for a coin flip, six for a die,
or any number,
and we just then said the state of a
system is a point in a set of
states,
however many we have.
And we also discussed the evolution of
the system in terms of arrows, which
took you from one state to the next to
the next to the next in discrete time
steps.
Thus far,
how far have we gotten by comparison
with this? Well, we've gotten to the
point where we've described what a state
is. We've gotten to the point, which is
about
the analog of the place where we would
be when I would say that a state is just
a point among a set of points, where the
set of points represents the space of
states.
Now, the space of states is a vector
space.
Well, we've gone a little bit beyond
that. We have also discussed
observables.
What would observables be in classical
physics? Observables would simply be
numbers which would label these states.
Functions, for example, we could assign
this state over here the observable
value some observable. Let's call it K
again.
Now, it wouldn't be a linear operator.
We would just call it K.
Ah,
here's a here's a good example of an
observable.
The head coin flip. The head We could
assign heads 1, and we could assign
tails minus 1.
What about the die? Well, the die
already comes
equipped with a numerical observable, 1
2 3 4 5 and 6. from relabeling
relabeling so that 6 became 1, 5 became
4, and mix them up in some funny way,
but
an observable then would just be an
assignment of a number to each state,
basically.
When the system moves around from one
point in the states in the state space
to another point, the observable
changes. So, when we flip the head and
coin the head and tail back and forth,
the head the the coin heads to tails to
heads to tails, we get a sequence of
observable values 1 -1 1 -1 1 -1. We can
imagine moving the die around in some
deterministic way, and again, it would
sweep out a series of values of the
observable.
There might be several observables.
Several different possible things that
we could numerical values we could
assign.
Okay.
Classical mechanics, of course, is
similar. The state space simply becomes
a continuous version of the same thing,
labeled by a set of coordinates and
momenta, labeled by a set of P's and
Q's.
So, the state space is still a set, but
it's a continuous set labeled by Q's and
P's.
Q's being coordinates, P being momenta.
Multidimensional space. Again, a state
is a point in that space.
And again, observables
are functions
of momentum and position, momenta and
positions. For example, one observable
might be P itself, the momentum.
That would just be a function which is
just P. It takes on different values at
different heights. Another observable
would just be Q.
P plus Q is an observable. All of them
would be functions of points on here.
Quantum mechanics extremely different.
How far have we gotten? We've gotten
about as far with quantum mechanics as I
have just described at approximately
what would be 4 minutes?
4 minutes in the classical context.
We've described what states are. They
are vectors in a vector space. I
actually have not even been complete
about that yet.
And we've described what observables
are. They're Hermitian operators.
Uh and it took us several weeks to get
to that point.
But now that we've gotten to that point,
we have uh we have some equipment now,
some um some
what's the word? Some tools
to go on and discuss the next sorts of
things, which are how how systems move.
Well, I'm not quite ready for that yet
because I do want to uh I do want to
review a little bit and to do
a little bit of mathematical formalism
which we haven't discussed yet.
First of all,
let me remind you what you do with
states when you have them. States are
vectors. They're the bra bra vectors and
ket vectors.
And there are two interesting,
physically interesting things that you
can do. Let us suppose you know the
state of a system
and you're interested in some
observable.
Well, one thing you can do is to compute
the average value of the observable, the
thing that most physicists call the
expectation value.
Let's call the observable again just K
for well,
yeah, K is fine.
Sometimes I remember to put the little
hat on top of it, sometimes I don't.
The average of it
is just a sandwich K
between the state the the ket version of
the state and the bra version of the
state.
That's the average.
And it would be something which would be
useful if you were going to measure K,
if you were going to prepare the system
in the same state over and over again.
And many, many measurements of K
and take the average would be a useful
thing to do. It's a physically
interesting quantity.
Another thing is supposing we have two
states.
Supposing we have A and B.
And as it happens, A and B are
eigenvectors of two different
observables.
Let's say that A is an eigenvector of K
with eigenvalue
let's call it
um
alpha
times A.
And let's suppose that B happens to be
an eigenvector of a totally different
observable
L
which happens to have eigenvalue beta
times B.
They're two eigenvectors but of
different operators.
Then the interesting quantity that we've
discussed over and over again, although
I haven't I may not have spelled it out
in quite this detail, is we could ask,
what's the probability
that we if we prepare a system
with an definite value of the observable
K,
namely alpha,
we do something to the system so as to
make K definite and namely with the
value of alpha, then what's the
probability that if we then measure L
that we get beta?
What's the probability that if we
measure L
we get the answer beta given that we
prepared the system
with a definite value of K, namely equal
to alpha?
The answer is
the inner product of A with B
squared.
Or another way to write it
is times its complex conjugate.
Which we can write as B times A.
That's equal
it's equal to two things in fact. We can
call it the probability AB.
It's the probability again that if we
prepare the state
with alpha
and then measure L that we get beta. But
it also happens to be the probability
that if we prepare the state
with L equals beta and then measure K
that we get alpha. Was that clear?
Well, it hardly matters since you get
the same answer.
Oh, did I write it wrong? You're right,
I did.
Right. This one is the complex conjugate
of this. Now, these are the two kinds of
questions that you ask in quantum
mechanics, average values for an
ensemble of many experiments, and again,
probabilities, which again only make
sense for for many repeated experiments.
Both of these have the feature
that
the answers are insensitive to a certain
operation that you can do on any one of
the vectors in the space.
And the operation is called multiplying
the vector by a phase. Oh, before I go
on, let me just remind you of one thing,
that physical state vectors always
should be normalized
to make the total probability equal to
one.
That's one rule.
So we can think of physical state
vectors as unit vectors.
Simply, that's the statement that the
sums of the squares of the coefficients
when you expand the the state in a
basis, those should add up to one.
All right. But let's discuss another
operation that you can do. You can take
a state, all the whole state, not not a
piece of it individually when you add up
pieces, but the whole state, the whole
vector,
and you can multiply it by a phase. And
I'm going to explain what that means in
a moment. But the point is it doesn't
make any difference whatever to the
physical properties of the state. All
right, so what is first what what does a
phase mean?
A phase is a complex number. Let's just
remember very quickly for those who are
uh
uh haven't
been using complex numbers for the last
50 years, a complex number is an X and a
Y with an X equal to IY.
It also can be represented as an R and a
theta.
And
it can be represented in the form X not
X X and X plus IY.
X plus IY, that's the complex number Z.
It can also be written in the form
R cosine theta, that's X
plus I R sine theta,
that's Y.
And another way of expressing it,
which is just more or less notation, is
to write it as R times E to the I theta.
E to the I theta is just another way of
writing cosine theta plus I sine theta.
Very quickly,
when you multiply two complex numbers,
you multiply their R's and you add their
angles.
So if we had two complex numbers, let's
call one of them RE to the I theta, the
other one let's call it um
what's another letter that's near R?
No.
Yes.
R1 and theta1 sorry, theta1.
And another complex number R2E to the I
theta2.
Adding them is easy in this form. We
just add the components. Multiplying
them is easy in this form. When you
multiply two complex numbers,
the result is R1R2.
You multiply the lengths
and then you add
the angles. E to the I theta1 plus
theta2.
One more point,
the notion of complex conjugate,
the complex conjugate of a complex
number is just the corresponding complex
number in the lower half plane,
which has exactly the same form R,
except instead of E to the I theta, it
has E to the minus I theta.
So whatever Z is, RE to the I theta,
Z star
is RE to the minus I theta.
Now, in particular, the special numbers,
which are called just pure phases,
special complex numbers,
for which R is equal to one.
They are the numbers which lie on the
unit circle.
The numbers which lie on the unit
circle,
in other words, for which R is equal to
one,
and theta can vary around from zero to
two pi,
those numbers are called phases. E Well,
actually, usually
uh the language is a little bit
ambiguous. Sometimes the angle is called
the phase, and sometimes any number
which is of the form e to the i times an
angle is called a phase.
All right. So, e to the i
theta is a special kind of number
which I will call a phase, even though
sometimes the phase is reserved for the
angle there.
Right? And has the property
that when you multiply it by its complex
conjugate, let's call this z.
If we multiply z times z star,
and if z is a pure phase,
then the result is just one. Why is
that? Because it's e to the i theta
times e to the minus i theta.
And when you multiply complex numbers,
you just add the phases,
and e to the zero is just one.
All right. So, this is a special class
of numbers which are characterized by z
times z star equal one.
Good.
Now, what does that have to do with
these vectors?
Formally,
or just mathematically,
we distinguish
two vectors. Let's call one of them A,
and let's call the other e to the i
theta
times A, where theta is any angle, a
number.
Right?
This is a vector. This is a number times
a vector.
Formally speaking, they're two different
vectors, just as a vector and twice the
vector are two different vectors.
So, mathematically speaking, this vector
is not equal to this vector.
But,
all of the physical properties of these
two are identical.
How to see that? Let's go back to the
various things
that we might uh do with or the various
physical questions we might ask.
For example, supposing we took psi here,
let's take the case of the expectation
value or the average value of any
observable at all.
Doesn't matter what it what it what K
is. Supposing we multiply psi
by e to the i theta.
If we multiply psi by e to the i theta,
what happens? In other words, if we
multiply
the ket by e to the i theta, what
happens to the corresponding bra?
Right. The corresponding bra is psi
e to the minus i theta.
So, what would happen if
in this sandwich, in this ket sandwich,
we replace the bread psi
by
e to the i theta times psi?
Well,
this the bra vector Sorry, the ket
vector would pick up the factor e to the
i theta.
This would get the factor e to the i
theta.
This one would get the factor e to the
minus i theta.
Now, remembering that e to the i theta
is just a number. It's not an
interesting operator of any kind.
E to the i theta times e to the minus i
theta is just one, and this would just
cancel out of the expression.
So, there would be no change in the
expectation value of any operator
if we replaced any vector, any one of
them,
uh
the vector which happens to describe the
system in particular, if we multiply it
by a phase. So, in that sense,
the phase is irrelevant.
We can choose the overall phase of the
state any way we like. Doesn't make any
difference to what uh to what we would
measure.
Likewise,
in the probability,
if we multiplied either A or B or both
by a phase, it would also cancel out
because, let's suppose we multiplied B
by a phase. The bra The ket vector over
here would get multiplied by a phase.
The bra vector over here would get
multiplied by the opposite phase, and
they would cancel.
You could do the same thing with A.
So, again, you see that there is no
physical significance to the phase of
the wave function.
The norm of the wave function should be
set equal to one,
and the phase of the wave function is
completely irrelevant.
Okay, let's come back for a moment to
polarization.
Polarization of photons.
I said, for example,
that the vector X
is equal to one zero,
and the vector Y
is equal to zero one.
Nothing would have stopped me from
replacing Y by a new version of itself,
namely zero minus one.
M- minus one. Multiplying by minus one
is multiplying by a phase.
E to the i pi
is equal to minus one.
So, a special case of multiplying a
state by a phase is just to multiply the
whole state by minus one.
I could have done it with X also. It
doesn't matter.
All of these are physically
This
is physically identical to
minus one zero.
It is also physically identical I
shouldn't put equals. They're not equals
as vectors.
Um what kind of symbol can I use?
Let's uh
It's Two squigglies means approximately
equal to. Not even approximately equal
to.
A dot over the equals. Okay. A dot over
the equals, which means has the same
physical significance as.
Cuz
that means something else.
We'll take the dot over the equals to
mean has the same physical significance
as.
All right.
Putting a minus one, but also we could
also multiply it by any phase.
E to the i theta zero.
All No, sorry.
Stop.
They all have the same physical meaning
as a state in which the polarization
lies in the horizontal direction.
Same thing with the polarization lying
in the
vertical direction.
We can multiply by minus one or anything
else.
Zero
e to the i theta.
Uh
Yeah, I love them.
But, I don't I'm not sure they're quite
right.
So, I will use the term
has the same physical significance as. I
know it's a lot of words, but uh
All right. For you, I'll use similar.
Is similar to.
All right.
Similar is something that has to do with
triangles, I thought. But, uh anyway,
let's uh let's move on.
Hm?
I don't know. It's just has the same
expectation values and probabilities.
That's all.
All right. So, we can come back to here
now, to these circular polarizations.
I could change the definition of the
circular polarization. For example, I
might multiply by i.
Supposing I took the uh positively
circularly polarized state, and changed
its definition by multiplying both top
and bottom by i, then this would become
similar to
in Mike's terminology, similar to
one over the square root of two.
Now, I'm going to multiply everything by
i. I is a pure phase. It's e to the i pi
over two.
One over the square root of two. i minus
one.
i times one is i.
i times i is minus one.
So, this has exactly the same physical
content as this one here.
In this particular case,
we can count parameters. We can now
count how many parameters it takes to
describe the polarization of a physical
photon,
the physical polarization state of a
photon.
Let's count.
All right. We can start with a general
vector.
Let's call it alpha beta.
That's two complex parameters, four real
numbers all together.
So, a general vector in the vector space
has four real parameters associated with
it.
Now, first of all, there is one
combination
that we set
and we freeze, namely alpha star alpha
plus beta star beta
is equal to one.
That's the condition that the sum of the
probabilities add up to one.
So, we started with four real
parameters,
one equation among them. How many are
left?
Three.
Okay, so there's three parameters left
over. Three
three parameters left over.
But,
now there is one more fact.
If we multiply by a phase, it doesn't
change the content of the uh, of the
state.
That means the overall phase
doesn't have any content. There's no
content in the overall phase.
Equivalently, I can always take the
upper entry to be real.
I can always multiply by the appropriate
phase.
You have to multiply the top and the
bottom by the same phase,
but we can always choose, for example,
this would be arbitrary, but we can
always choose to make the upper
component real by multiplying by the
appropriate phase to get rid
of the complex part of alpha here.
So, we can always choose alpha to be
real.
Now that it's real, let's give it
another name,
A.
I'll use Latin letters for the moment
for real numbers
and complex numbers down here, beta.
All right, so how many do I have left?
Um,
let's first of all solve this
relationship here.
We have to have that the sums of the
squares
we have to have that A squared
plus beta star beta
equals one.
There's an easy way to solve that. We
just write that beta star beta
is 1 minus A squared.
And now we can write that beta
is equal to the square root of 1 minus A
squared
times any phase,
E to the I theta.
If beta star times beta is a number,
that means that beta is the square root
of that number times a phase.
General fact
follows from
the definition of beta star and beta.
All right, so we can now write that the
most general possibility is a real
number up here. Again, I choose a real
number arbitrarily here.
Then, to make sure that it's normalized,
I put 1 minus A squared square root down
here, but then I still have the freedom
to put in a phase, E to the I theta.
How many overall parameters are there?
Two. One real parameter here
and one real parameter for theta.
So, that means there's a two-parameter
family,
a two-parameter family
of
polarization states for a single photon.
What are
those two parameters? Physically, why
are there two parameters associated with
the polarization of a photon?
So, let's come back to an
electromagnetic wave.
The simple the simplest electromagnetic
wave is a wave which is polarized whose
electric field is along a particular
axis.
All right, so the wave is going into the
blackboard.
It's polarization is along some axis
which we label theta.
Plane polarization.
That's only one parameter. And then
incidentally, it's not the same as this
theta here.
Uh,
that's only one parameter. That
polarization could lie along any
direction,
but if it's a plane polarized wave,
it then
uh, has a there's a one-parameter family
of them corresponding simply to the
direction of the electric field, the
direction of the electric field theta.
Now,
if I combine two waves
with two different polarizations
and the electric fields are in phase
with each other.
For example, they're both cosines.
Uh, we add
then if the polarization if the electric
fields are in phase with each other,
it just gives you a polarization in a
different direction.
But if the
two directions of polarization are out
of phase with respect to each other,
then the electric field can sweep out a
circle,
but it can also sweep out an ellipse.
For example, here's a wave that sweeps
out an ellipse.
The X component of the electric field
is equal to cosine
of X minus CT.
And if I take EY
equal to sine of X minus CT,
then
if I stand, let's say, at X equals zero
and watch what's happening, the electric
field moves on a circle.
That's circularly polarized light.
All right. But if I take EY to be 1/2 of
that,
now
the electric field in the Y direction
only grows to half the size
of its maximum in the X direction.
I don't think I drew that well.
That becomes elliptical polarization.
It's elliptical polarization, but it's
described by a major and minor axis, the
major axis in this case being along the
X axis.
We can consider rotated versions of
that.
We can imagine combining electric fields
together in such a way as to create
elliptical polarization
along an arbitrary axis.
In other words, with the major axis
being along any axis.
That's one variable,
the angle of the
major axis.
And the other variable being the
eccentricity of the ellipse,
the ratio the aspect ratio of the small
diameter to the large diameter.
That is the other uh, parameter.
So, there are two parameters describing
the polarization. One is the angle of
the major axis
and the other is the eccentricity of the
ellipse, two real parameters.
Now, there are some special cases.
When the eccentricity goes to zero,
it becomes plane
eccentricity goes to zero means it
collapses to an infinitely thin
ellipse,
then it becomes plane polarized.
In the limit that the eccentricity goes,
I suppose you would say to one,
uh, then it becomes circularly
polarized.
And in that situation, theta doesn't
matter anymore. For a perfect circularly
polarized photon, there's no special
axis for the major axis. But in general,
in the arbitrary in the generic
situation,
two parameters two real parameters to
describe the polarization of a photon.
And so it's not so surprising
that we found two real parameters
describing the state of a photon.
Somehow these two real parameters are in
one-to-one correspondence. Some
functions of them are the eccentricity
of the ellipse and the
uh, rotational axis of the ellipse. Not
the rotational axis, the um,
the long axis of the ellipse.
I'm not going to tell you how to
Shall I tell you how to find out the
which is which?
Okay, I'll tell you what you I'll tell
you what you can do.
Yeah.
Say again.
Uh,
actually, yeah. Um,
okay, I'll good.
All right. So, there's one parameter
which corresponds to the eccentricity of
the ellipse. It starts at circular
polarization and it starts to squash
down and it goes to zero. If you go past
zero,
just go right past zero,
then the polarization changes uh, the
polarization goes in the other
direction. In other words, if this is
rotating this way
and we squeeze it and squeeze it and
squeeze it until the lower part of the
ellipse passes the upper part of the
ellipse, then it rotates the other way.
So,
the two parameters are enough to
to describe both polarizations. When
some number goes negative, it describes
the other polarization.
Yeah, right. You can think of it as
negative eccentricity. Right.
Right. But supposing, for example, I
wanted to find the direction of the
major axis.
Well, here's what I suspect. I would
expect I could ask the question,
what is the probability that if I
measure the linear polarization along an
axis theta, that I'll get plus one or
minus one?
All right. So, let me first ask, given
this circular polarization here,
and in fact, I better change the I
better change the name of this angle
here.
I'm going to call it phi.
All right.
Now, let's take a linear polarized
photon.
Or let's take a state of linear
polarization.
As this one here.
That was described by cosine theta
sine theta.
And now let's ask supposing we start
with this photon and instead of
measuring the circular polarization or
the elliptical polarization, let's
measure
the linear polarization along the axis
theta. That means put a polarizer or a
linear polarizer along the direction
theta and see what the probability that
you go through is. What's the
probability that it's polarized along
the theta axis? Well, it's just the
inner product
of the state of the photon with the
eigenstate describing a particular
polarization squared. So, the
probability that this photon
is that this
uh elliptically polarized photon
is measured
along the theta axis if I were to
measure the plane polarization
what is that going to be? It's going to
be the inner product of this with this
squared. Let's write down that inner
product. It's cosine theta times A.
Let's call this Let's see we call this
theta.
And this
uh psi.
Okay. So, what is psi theta? Inner
product of psi with theta.
Psi with theta
it's A
times cosine theta
plus
square root
of 1 minus A squared E to the I theta
No, E to the I phi.
times sine theta.
Do I have it right?
Doesn't one of them have to be
conjugated? So, either minus I theta
Yeah.
One of them should be conjugated. Good.
E to the minus I theta. E to the minus I
phi. This is not yet the probability.
Let's compute the probability. We
multiply this by its complex conjugate.
Right.
Uh do we really want to carry this out?
I don't really want to carry it out, but
I want to tell you what you do with it
when you find it.
When you find it, you will then know the
probability that this particular photon
is polarized along the theta axis.
Now, how do we find the major axis
associated with psi?
We maximize the probability
with respect to theta.
We look for the direction theta which
maximizes the probability
that this photon lies along this
direction.
So, what we would do is to multiply this
by its complex conjugate. That's too
hard for me. I I I don't feel like doing
that. Yeah.
Do I feel like doing it? No, definitely
not. Multiply this by its complex
conjugate. Homework Homework assignment.
Multiply this by its complex conjugate.
Think of phi as fixed. Phi is the fixed
parameter associated with this photon.
And we're going to adjust this axis
until we maximize until we have the best
fit until the linear polarization
uh maximizes the probability
maximizes the overlap with this
elliptical polarization here. Maximizes
the inner product or the square of the
inner product. That will tell you what
the major axis of psi is. It's more or
less intuitively clear that whatever the
major axis of psi is, in other words, if
it corresponds to a
elliptical polarization in in this
direction and then we measure the
linear polarization in different
directions
that the that the
that the probability will be maximized
when the linear polarization max
matches the um
uh the diameter of the the major
diameter of the ellipse.
All right. So, you think of think of phi
as fixed square this
and maximize it with respect to theta.
In other words, differentiate with
respect to theta and find the place
where it's maximum. That will tell you
the angle of the major axis.
The eccentricity you can
uh
Okay, the eccentricity would have to do
with the difference of the probability
that the photon uh lied along that
direction or along that direction.
In other words,
uh
if you find
that there's a very high probability
that this elliptic photon is polarized
along some linear direction, that will
mean the eccentricity is small
and the difference between the two
probabilities is some measure of the uh
of the uh
asymmetry of the ellipse.
I didn't really mean to get into this. I
just really only wanted to point out to
you that there are two parameters
that govern the physics of a particular
state vector and that those two
parameters
are in one-to-one correspondence with
the two parameters associated with the
angle and eccentricity of the uh of the
ellipse. Yeah. So, it it seems like then
the sense counterclockwise or clockwise
Say it again. The
The Well, you have two parameters. You
have the orientation and eccentricity,
but what seems to be missing is
the sense
of whether it's clockwise
Okay. Well, somebody just asked me that
and I thought I answered it, but let me
go through it again.
The eccentricity
is a parameter
which can be negative or positive.
You start with an ellipse which looks
like this which is rotating in this
direction here. Well, let's start with a
circle. Circularly polarized is not
eccentric at all. Goes in this
direction.
Let's draw an axis in there. Doesn't
matter which axis, any axis in there.
And now start changing the eccentricity
by squeezing the ellipse. We squeeze the
ellipse and it goes down to here.
All right. Now, eccentricity you would
think ends at the point where it's
linearly polarized.
At that point, the eccentricity goes to
zero. I think it's counted as zero.
Right? The eccentricity becomes zero
when it collapses to a line. But you can
keep going. You can make the
eccentricity negative. When it goes
negative, these two pass each other.
The upper branch here which is moving
from the bottom to the top becomes the
lower branch and the lower branch
becomes the upper branch. So, the point
is the real parameters you vary the two
real parameters here over their entire
range, positive and negative, you pick
up both the both senses of polarization
as well as angle and uh
Okay?
Good.
All right. Now, our next
step is to understand how
uh how
the states change with time. That's the
big uh next step. How do they change
with time?
The analog
Oops. No.
The analog of the classical question
if we start with a space of states which
is just a bunch of points
how do you move from one to the next?
Now, with just a set of discrete points
you would have to imagine a kind of
stroboscopic time evolution
where you would divide time into little
intervals and at each instant or at each
interval make a jump from one state to
the next. There would be no way to do
this continuously.
In quantum mechanics, you can have a
finite dimensional vector space. For
example, just uh the uh the two
directions of polarization
but you can have continuous time
evolution. And the continuous time
evolution goes through the fact that you
have sort of continuous interpolations
between states. You have not only 1 0
and 0 1 but you have continuous
interpolations between them.
For example, the polarization vector
could rotate with time. That would not
be circular polarization. The linear
polarization could rotate with time.
That's a possible motion of the
polarization of a photon with time.
And although any time you measure the
polarization along the axis, you only
get one of two answers as if it were a
coin plus or minus nevertheless, the
time evolution of it can be completely
continuous and does not require that you
think stroboscopically.
So, quantum mechanics can have
discreteness of possibilities and still
have evolution which is continuous.
The question is how do we describe the
evolution of quantum systems?
Now, let's go back for a moment to the
evolution of classical systems.
When a classical system evolves,
it's just a permutation of the states.
The relationship between states stays
the same. Now, there's only one
relationship between states in classical
physics. Well, states I now mean this
discrete system,
heads and tails or
dice or whatever, some finite number of
states.
Right? That's all there are. There's
just a finite number of states. There's
only one relationship
between them that makes any sense.
They're either the same state or they're
different.
That's the only uh that's the only
relationship uh between them. They're
the same or they're different.
If they're different, we call them
different. If they're the same, we call
them the same.
One of the features of classical physics
is a conservation law
that says that with time, different
states will maintain their differences.
In other words, it will not happen
that two different states, let's call it
A over here and B over here,
will both evolve to C.
If they both evolve to C,
then you would lose the distinction
between the starting point.
If they both went to C,
for example,
if our rule of evolution
for dice
was that five goes to three
and two goes to three, and then a whole
bunch of other ones here, then if we
arrived at three, we wouldn't know if we
came from five or two.
That's not allowed in classical
uh physics. Evolution which sort of
loses distinctions.
Right? So, if two states start different
and they evolve with time, they stay
different. Right? That's the basic
conservation of relationships between
states.
The corresponding thing in quantum
mechanics
is very, very similar. The relationship
between states is maintained with time.
What is the relationship between two
states?
Right?
You can say they're different or they're
the same.
So, supposing I have two states,
let's call them A and B again,
Of
course, what it means for them to be the
same is that A equals B.
They are the same vector.
What does it mean for them to be
different?
Well, now we have to decide exactly what
we mean.
Yeah, we could put that here.
Fine.
We could put that there.
It would mean that they are equal up to
a phase.
We could use a stronger form of equal.
Uh but then remember that uh that we're
not really interested in uh in
distinctions which are only distinctions
of phase.
But we could put the dot there if we
like. But what is the concept of two
states being different? Well, it could
just be A equals not B.
But you could have two vectors, for
example,
two polarization states, one which is
polarized horizontally and one which is
polarized almost horizontally.
If we were to take that photon which was
polarized almost horizontally
and measure its horizontal polarization,
we might in fact discover that it was
horizontally polarized. In other words,
it might go through the horizontal
polarizer.
There's only one state which is
absolutely forbidden from going through
that horizontal polarizer and for which
we could definitively say that the
photon
was different than the horizontally
polarized photon. It's the vertically
polarized photon. The vertically
polarized photon will not go through the
polarizer.
So,
we could say that the vertically
polarized photon is orthogonal to the
horizontally polarized photon. The
orthogonality relationship is the
relationship which is the analog of
classically different. Measurably
different than a single experiment that
you can tell with one experiment that it
is one thing and not the other.
So, that's the relationship that we
would like to express, the relationship
of different. And that relationship is
that BA is equal to zero.
Or
BA is equal to
one, which would say well, which would
say they were the same.
More generally, the relationship between
two states is the overlap between them.
It tells you how similar they are.
Right?
If there's an overlap between states, it
means that there's a finite probability
that if you choose to measure one thing,
you'll get you know what I mean, the
point is. If AB
is not equal to zero, but for example,
close to one,
then the two states are quite a bit
alike.
And if you measure some observable which
would distinguish them,
well, they simply won't be well
distinguished.
So,
the important relationship between
states is inner product. If it's zero,
they're different.
If it's one, they're the same.
Right? If it's one, they're the same.
Remember that they are normalized
states. The only way that the inner
product can be one is if they're the
same.
All right, or the inner product can be
zero, in which case they're orthogonal,
or it can be anything in between.
This is the basic relationship between
states,
the inner product between them.
Now, just as in classical mechanics,
distinctions or relationships between
states are maintained with time.
States which are different stay
different as time evolves.
In quantum mechanics, the basic rule is
as a system evolves,
the inner product between its states
stays fixed.
In other words, as time goes on, let's
suppose we start a system
with state A.
Another identical system we start with
B.
A and B have to have an inner product
between them. And we let them run with
time. A runs to A prime.
B runs to B prime after a certain amount
of time. The state vector changes
in precise analogy with the way the
state might move around in uh
in the space of states
in classical reasoning.
A goes to A prime. A prime need not be
orthogonal to A. It'll just go to
something else, A prime. And at the same
time, B, if we started the system with
B, it would go to B prime.
The basic
conservation of information idea,
the basic conservation of distinctions
or relationships between states
simply says
that the inner product of B prime with A
prime
is the same as the inner product of B
with A.
In other words, for example, if A and B
are the same state,
then after they evolve, A prime and B
prime will be the same.
If A and B are orthogonal
and you run them for a while,
then the result will remain orthogonal.
That's the basic assumption of time
evolution in quantum mechanics,
that the relationships between states
stays fixed with time. Now, you can can
we derive that? No, I don't think we can
derive it.
Uh it's an observed fact,
but it comes together with a lot of uh
connections, a lot of connections with
things that you do know, such as energy
conservation.
Uh so, for the moment, let's just take
it as a given that relationships between
states
are maintained with time.
And try to figure out what that means.
Yeah.
Well, you don't.
You don't know.
The point is
that
if you have if you have made
a photon which is horizontal and you
then send it to a vertical
polarizer, you know with certainty that
it that it will be bounced. Every time
you do it.
You can make a whole bunch of
horizontally polarized photons. Every
one of them won't get through.
Well, uncertainty principle doesn't
doesn't say that there's any uh
any necessary uncertainty in the
direction of polarization of a photon.
Direction of polarization of a photon is
just one thing.
It usually takes two things to define an
uncertainty relation.
But, uh
you can you can
polarize a photon as accurately as you
like
if you can hold your polarizer still
enough and your polarizer is perfectly
perfectly aligned.
So,
there's no restriction on uh
on
fixing the polarization along a given
axis.
What you can't do is have the
polarization be known along two
different axes.
There's no state in which the photon is
known to be able to go through a
polarization in this direction and in
this direction.
So, it's an uncertainty between
polarizations in different directions.
Not an uncertainty in your ability to
polarize a photon along a given axis.
All right. So, in order to implement
this idea, well, well, let's let's just
discuss it a little bit more. Um
roughly speaking, what it says, if we
don't worry too much about the complex
aspects of complex vector spaces,
and we just think of ordinary vector
spaces, let's say in three dimensions,
then
we can imagine that with time
the state of vector of a system, this
could represent the state vector of a
system,
it moves with time.
It moves around with time just uh so
that the system evolves, properties of
the system change with time, but it
evolves in such a way that if two states
are orthogonal to a from to each other
to begin with, they stay orthogonal to
each other.
Right?
It's a kind of rotation of the space of
states which keeps angles fixed. Angles
between vectors stay fixed.
That's the assumption here. The angles
between vectors in the space of states
stay fixed and don't vary with time,
although the vectors themselves may vary
with time.
So,
uh
that's the idea that we want to
implement. To implement it, we need some
more mathematics. We need the
mathematics of unitary operators.
And we haven't discussed that yet, so
when we come back from a 5-minute break,
we'll discuss
a little more about her mission
and then unitary operators.
Unitary operators are the operators
which preserve relationships between
vectors.
So, let's take a break for 5 minutes.
Okay, let's get started. Now, we need to
we need to get some mathematical
concepts.
So, some of this is a little bit repeat,
but uh let's go through it anyway.
Let's suppose we have a linear operator
which is defined to act on the vector
space of kets.
Thus far, we have really defined linear
operators. Let's call it L, a linear
operator.
Put a little hat on it to indicate that
it's an a linear operator.
And it's defined through its action on
ket vectors.
So, given an A,
the linear operator acts on it to give
another vector which I've called C. Now,
you may wonder what happened to B. Well,
B will come back, but for the moment,
let's just call this C.
Every A, you can act on it and it will
give you some C. That's a linear
operator. Well, that's an opera that's
an operation. The fact that it's linear
entails certain conditions that it acts
on the sum of vectors to give back sums
and so forth and so on. I won't go
through that again.
But, given a linear operator who which
is defined in terms of its action on
kets, we can also define its action on
bra vectors in the following way.
I wish to define Now, this is
definition, but it's obviously a neat
definition. I wish to define the
operation of L
on a bra vector B.
All right.
So, L acts on B and it gives us some new
bra vector. That's the assumption. When
L acts on B,
it gives a new bra vector. How am I
going to find that bra vector?
Let's put in here a basis of vectors
and sum over N.
According to the principle that when you
sum over N,
that you get the identity,
sum on N of N N
is the identity operator.
I haven't done anything.
This is L on B.
Okay? But now, I can define
this object over here, oops, let's see.
This object over here
in the obvious way. Let L act to the
right on a ket vector. We know how L
acts on every ket vector. That's
implicit in the definition of a linear
operator that we know how it acts on any
ket vector.
So, instead of allowing L to act on the
bra vector to the left, interpret the
symbol as L acting on the ket vector to
the right and then taking the inner
product with B.
We can define this matrix element. It's
called a matrix element. It's a
sandwich, in this case with two
different kinds of bread, A and B,
with the bologna in between being the
linear operator L.
And we define it even though
we're imagining that L is acting to the
left, let's nevertheless define a single
symbol
by defining this by defining L acts to
the right on N and then we take the
inner product with B.
That gives us a definition
of
L
acting on a bra vector.
Are you assuming L is Hermitian?
No, not yet. No, not particularly.
L is not Hermitian or can be Hermitian,
but it's not. But, it's not necessarily.
Question is associativity
of the
B
Let's see. Have I assumed associativity?
I probably I always assume
associativity. Beyond L
Yeah. Yeah, that's right. Yeah.
Yeah. That's right. We've assumed Now,
this is this is definition, if you like.
This is definition, but it's clearly a
neat definition
which will allow us to do all sorts of
manipulations in a sort of mechanical
way without thinking very hard. That's
the uh
that's the purpose of a good notation.
To not have to think very hard when you
use it and to use it by inspection.
All right. So, this is the definition.
The answer is a bra vector. These are
numbers. These are all numbers and they
multiply bra vectors N.
And so, the result is a bra vector. And
this then defines for us how the same
operator which was defined to act to the
to the right on ket vectors acts to the
left on bra vectors.
So, linear operators can act either way,
either to the left or to the right.
And the notation has purposefully been
made
so that
if we have a sandwich,
I'm giving up on this one.
If we have a sandwich,
B
L hat
A
we can interpret this in one of two
ways.
The inner product of B
with Let's put a big bracket around it,
using now the associativity.
L hat
acting on A
or
as L hat acting to the left on B
and then inner product with A.
That's the that's the point of this
particular construction.
It doesn't matter whether we think of L
hat acting on A and then inner product
with B or L hat acting on B and then
inner product with A.
Let's define the Hermitian conjugate of
an operator A L.
Supposing L is some linear operator
such that when it acts on any vector A,
it gives us
a vector that I'll call C.
Okay?
This is a correspondence. It's a mapping
of vectors into vectors, all right?
Starting with an A, you get a C and L is
thought of as a mapping.
There's a corresponding mapping
which maps bra vectors.
Some operator
if if L maps A to C, ket vectors, then
there's some object which I'm going to
call L
dagger
or the Hermitian conjugate of L,
which acts the same way
except among bra vectors. So, if there's
a correspondence between every bra every
ket vector and a bra vector,
then I can also look for a
correspondence between operators
so that given an operator L which takes
A to C, there must be some other
operator which acts to the left on bra
vectors which induces a kind of parallel
uh
mapping, mapping among the bra vectors
which is the image of the mapping among
the ket vectors.
What's the connection between L dagger,
this is also an operator.
What's the connection between this
operator and this operator? They're not
the same necessarily.
In fact, they're kind of complex
conjugates of each other.
This uh dagger here which is called
Hermitian conjugate is a kind of complex
conjugation. It's not just simple
conjugation, it's a little more than
that. But, since the bra vector A is the
complex conjugate of the ket vector A
and the bra vector C is the complex
conjugate of the ket vector C, you
wouldn't be too far off if you were to
say somehow this Hermitian conjugation
is representing some form of complex
conjugation. And in fact, it is.
Let's see if we can find the
relationship
between
L and L dagger. To do that, let's take
the inner product of the top equation
with B.
So, here's our equation. Now, we're
going to come over to here, take the
inner product B
L hat
A.
And what is that?
That's B
C.
I've just taken some arbitrary vector B,
any vector B, and sandwiched or taken
the inner product of both sides of this
equation with B.
Now, let's take the inner product of
this equation, not with the bra vector
B, but with the ket vector B.
That says that A
L hat dagger, there's too many symbols.
I really don't need that hat, do I?
There's really not much lost if I were
to leave the hats off the operators, but
uh let's leave them. B.
I've now taken the inner product of this
side with the ket vector B, and that's
equal to
C B.
Now, what's the connection between the
two right hand sides here?
They're complex conjugates of each
other.
If I take the inner product of two
vectors, but then I take them in the
opposite order,
invert bra to ket and ket to bra, then
these are complex conjugates of each
other. So, these two are complex
conjugates, and it follows that these
two are complex conjugates. So, now we
can write down
one of the connections between an
operator and its Hermitian conjugate.
And here it is right here,
that every matrix element
of the original operator L
is related
to the com or is equal to the complex
conjugate of the Hermitian conjugate,
but with the bras and the kets
interchanged.
In other words, to go from an operator
to its Hermitian conjugate,
you interchange bras and kets, and you
complex conjugate.
Now,
let's uh let's consider
a useful defining
a useful way to
define complex conjugation now.
We can define it in terms of a basis.
Supposing we have a basis of vectors,
and we consider the inner products N
L
conjugate M.
If we know all of these
If we know all of the matrix elements,
matrix elements in a basis, and we can
call these things L N M.
If we know all of these matrix elements,
then we know everything there is to know
about the operator. Yeah.
For the moment, let's assume finite
dimension. Yeah.
I am assuming finite dimension, but
everything I say also applies to the
infinite dimensional case.
So,
you can think of taking the limit where
the dimension of the vector space gets
very, very big.
Okay.
What's that?
Thank you.
I do.
Right.
That is equal to This is This is yet to
be defined, though this is the we assume
that we know
the matrix elements of L.
But, this is equal to
the complex conjugate
of the matrix element of L with the bras
and the kets interchanged and complex
conjugated. That's what this says over
here. Interchange
bras and kets and complex conjugate.
All right? So, we now know that we can
now write an equation
that Well, this of course is equal to L
M N.
So, here's the rule.
If you have an operator represented as
a matrix L M N. So, transpose and
complex conjugate combined together to
form Hermitian conjugate.
Easy idea, not very hard.
Now, the class of operators which are
their own Hermitian conjugates are the
Hermitian operators. So, the Hermitian
operators are the ones the special ones
which satisfy L is equal to L dagger.
In terms of matrix elements,
first of all, it says that the diagonal
matrix elements must be real.
It says that L11 must equal L11 star.
All right? So, on the diagonal, if this
is to be equal to this, if L is to be
equal to L Hermitian conjugate,
then it says
L11 equals L11 star. Well, that just
says that L11 is real. Likewise for L22
and so forth.
So, the diagonal elements of a Hermitian
of a Hermitian
matrix are all real.
L I I
is real.
And then, as far as the off-diagonal
elements, let's
As far as the off-diagonal elements go,
they have the property
that if you reflect about the diagonal,
they're replaced The element is replaced
by its complex conjugate.
So, Hermitian operators, this is L21
star.
L22 is real.
L13 should be L31 star, so that's L31
L13 star.
This is L23 star.
And so forth.
L33 is real.
All right, so the rule for a hermitian
operator is that the diagonal elements
are real and the off-diagonal elements
the images the mirror images are complex
conjugates of each other.
That's a hermitian operator.
Hermitian operators, remember I I'll
just remind you, hermitian operators
have the property that their expectation
values are real.
Their eigenvalues are real.
And their eigenvectors are mutually
orthogonal for different values of the
eigenvalue.
All right, we've gone through that
before. Hermitian operators are the ones
which correspond to
to observables.
Well, it depends on how many independent
states of a system there are.
Well, again, it depends on what we're
studying. If we isolate out as an
interesting system just the polarization
of a photon and don't worry about
anything else, they're 2x2 matrices.
If we want to study a whole photon, then
they become infinite-dimensional
matrices because we have to take into
account either the position or the
momentum of the photon which can have
any value.
So, in most real quantum mechanical
systems, in fact in any real quantum
mechanical system, they're really
infinite matrices.
All right? But infinite matrices are
hard to write on the blackboard.
They're a little bit um
Easy but tedious, yeah.
Uh
So
And it's always the case that in or
almost always the case that in practice
we approximate the system by a finite
number of states to actually do
calculations.
Not always, but in most cases we
approximate by uh by finite-dimensional
matrices. Okay. So, for example
Uh a particle moving on a line where the
particle can be anywhere. Well, we can
approximate that by a particle which can
exist anywheres in some very very dense
collection of positions.
Well, still we have an infinite number
of points going between minus infinity
and plus infinity.
Nothing uh too bad happens if instead of
going out to infinity we go out to
Brooklyn in this direction and uh in
Hong Kong in this direction
and just make it very big. And so we
work with very very large numerically
very very large matrices
as an approximation to the
infinite-dimensional case. Is analytic
analytical reduction of states analogous
to this?
Analytic reduction of states, I don't
know what it means. Okay.
Good. So, we have the idea of hermitian
matrices and these are the things which
define or which are connected with
observables. Real eigenvalues, real
expectation values.
And orthogonal mutually orthogonal
eigenvectors.
They are not the things that we identify
with transformations of the vector space
that preserve relationships. Remember
our goal now is to find the operations
which where are they? Which which um
which preserve relationships between
vectors.
I don't know. I erased it off the
blackboard.
So, these are not the operations
which correspond to the
preservers of relations.
Let's try to define those. Oh,
incidentally, let's just check first of
all that our polarization observables
are hermitian.
We had three of them.
We had one which was 1 -1 0 0.
All right.
The only rule is for them to be
hermitian is that the on-diagonal
elements should be real and the
off-diagonal elements when reflected
should be complex conjugates of each
other. This obviously has this property.
Real on-diagonal and the off-diagonals
are in fact complex conjugates of each
other, zero being its own complex
conjugate.
All right, then we had another one which
was 0 1 1 0.
This was
And again, on-diagonal elements real,
zero is real, off-diagonal elements
complex conjugates of each other. And
the last one
which was P
for circular polarization
that was
-i i
0 0.
On-diagonal real, off-diagonal complex
conjugates of each other.
Okay? So, these three are hermitian
and uh satisfy the rules of uh being
observables.
Okay, now we come to unitary operators.
Unitary operators are the ones which
preserve relationships. So, let's define
what that means.
Yes.
Yes, but it makes good sense. The things
that you actually observe and measure
are always real numbers.
The objects whose expectation values are
always real for every vector, that's
another way to define the hermitians.
It's equivalent that if you take any
pair of vec- any any vector psi
uh L psi if if for any psi this is real
then it follows that L is hermitian.
Now, I haven't proved that. But that's
it's a couple of lines. It really is
very fast to prove that if L is
hermitian, then psi L psi is real and
vice versa. That's a that's a fast
a simple theorem.
So, the reality of the expectation
value, which makes good sense for a
observable, and also the reality of the
eigenvalues, which are the possible
values that you can measure
those are um
you know, the key signature of things
that you actually observe in the
laboratory.
The eigenvectors of a hermitian operator
span the vector space.
That is not generally true of
non-hermitian operators. It can be true,
but it's not necessarily true.
Complete set of mutually orthogonal
eigenvectors.
Right.
Now, you can have a complete set of
eigenvectors which aren't orthogonal to
each other.
That can happen and then the operator
would not be a hermitian.
Or it could fail to have a complete set
of
What's that?
Yeah, you can have there are operators
that don't have any eigenvectors.
Yeah.
Oh, definitely not. It certainly would
not be hermitian since every hermitian
operator has a complete set of
eigenvectors.
A complete orthonormal
An equivalent definition of hermitian is
that it has a complete orthonormal
collection of eigenvectors with real
eigenvalues.
Right? That's a an equivalent
definition.
All right, but now we're interested not
in observables but in transformations of
the vector space.
The transformations could could
correspond to a number of things. They
could define the way the system evolves
with time. How
vectors transform under into other
vectors under time evolution. It could
correspond to symmetries.
What are the vectors for example? Here's
a here's an example.
Uh
Given a polarization vector
given a polarization state
theta
we can imagine symmetry operations which
rotate the polarize the the plane of the
polarization.
We could say supposing we're interested
now in an operation which rotates the
polarization vector by a certain angle.
That
that is also a transformation on the
space of states. Just the rotation of
the polarization vector. There's all
kinds of transformations we could do.
And we're interested in those
transformations which preserve the
relationships between the vectors.
So, let's see if we can't get a handle
on that idea.
Take any two vectors in the vector
space, A and B. Our favorite two vectors
again, A and B.
Let's take their inner product AB.
In some sense that defines the
relationship between the two vectors.
The degree to which they're similar or
not similar.
Zero, they're orthogonal, there is
dissimil- dissimilar as possible.
One, and they're
equal as similar as possible.
Now,
uh
let's imagine a transformation which can
act on any vector. Let's call it U. U
stands for unitary, but for the moment
we don't even know what that means.
So, let U on A
is equal to A prime.
For every A, there's an A prime obtained
by acting with some linear operator
called U.
All right?
Of course, we can I don't know why I
wrote A here. I think I should have
written B.
B prime.
B prime, B and B prime are just labels.
They could They can run over any vector
in the vector space.
Now, the same
operation has an image
among the bra vectors.
Remember, if an operation takes place
among the ket vectors, the image of it
involves the Hermitian conjugate. So, if
this is true, then
the same operation, except when
interpreted in terms of bra vectors,
will involve U dagger.
All right. So, let let me let me write
this correctly.
Supposing U takes B
to B prime.
And supposing U takes A
to A prime.
What does U do?
Or what Excuse me.
Then it follows
that A U dagger
is equal to bra vector A prime. That's
the definition of the Hermitian
conjugate. If U on A equals A prime,
then U dagger on bra vector A equals bra
vector A prime.
Okay.
Now, let's take Now, let's consider
the relationship between AB
and A prime B prime. And let's require
them to be equal.
In other words, whatever U does, it
doesn't disturb the relationship between
vectors.
It hits A
and gives A prime. It hits B and gives B
prime, but it doesn't disturb the
relationship, meaning that the inner
product of the outputs is the same as
the inner product of the inputs.
So, what does that say? Let's just write
it down. Substituting for A prime, U
dagger A,
this is equal
to
A
U dagger.
That's A prime, but then B prime is U
times B.
Okay? Simply stated, B prime has been
re- replaced by U times B, A prime has
been replaced by U dagger times A.
But this should be true. Let's
get rid of the intermediate step here.
Let's get rid of this.
Here is what we require
of the transformation U.
If U preserves the relationships, then
for any pair of vectors A and B,
A U dagger U B
should be equal to AB.
But if a thing like this is true for any
pair of vectors,
if for any vectors, any A and B,
sticking an operator in between them
does nothing at all,
then it follows, this is a theorem,
that U dagger U
must be the identity operator.
If you have some operator
that when you sandwich it between any
two vectors,
gives you back the inner product without
the operator, then that operator is the
unit operator. That's a theorem. That's
easy to prove again
that if A U dagger U times B is equal to
AB not just for one particular pair of
vectors, but for any vectors in the
vector space,
then it follows that U dagger U is the
identity operator. It does not say that
U is the identity operator. It says U
dagger times U is the identity operator.
In other words, U dagger undoes whatever
U does. Whatever U does, if you multiply
it by U dagger, it undoes it.
That says that U dagger is the inverse
of U.
U dagger times U is one says that U
dagger is the inverse operator of U.
Another way to write the same thing is
that U dagger
is the inverse of U.
Meaning just the operator
that undoes whatever U does.
Operators with this property that U
dagger times U
uh the identity operator, those are
called unitary.
They are They are not themselves
identity operators. They can shift the
vectors around, but they shift them
around in a way which preserves the
relationships.
All right?
That's the unitary operators. All
operators which preserve relationships
are unitary.
So,
um
Yeah. Are you using relationships
in any broader sense than just
preserving the inner product? That's all
I mean That's all I mean by it.
Mathematically, that's what I mean by
it.
Physically, of course, it means it um
it preserves
the
if you like, we can call this the square
of this, we can call it the probability
that if B then A.
I'm choosing shorthand for something
much more complicated. If B then A,
uh that the relationship um is
preserved. For example, with time, if U
represents the time evolution of a
system.
So, okay. So, this is the class of
unitary operators. U dagger U is equal
to one.
We have only a couple of minutes.
So, I'm going to tell you now some of
the properties of unitary operators,
which uh some of which we will prove,
some of which you can find in books, and
some of which are obvious.
First of all,
in fact, I'm just going to tell you the
properties. I'm not going to justify
them right now.
Unitary operators have one feature in
common with Hermitian operators. They
also have
complete orthonormal sets of
eigenvectors.
All right? So, there's a complete ba-
There exists for each unitary a complete
basis N
such that U on N
gives an eigenvalue lambda N times N.
But, the eigenvalues are definitely not
real.
Oh, they can be real, but in general,
they're certainly not in general real
numbers.
The lambdas do have a special property.
Let's see if we can figure out what that
property is.
If U has a complete set of eigenvalues,
what can we say about the eigenvalues?
So, let's use the fact
Oh.
Uh let's see.
I think I'm running I think we're I
think we'll quit at this point.
I think we'll quit at this point. Let's
Let's just quit. Let's stop now. Let's
stop now, and next week we will consider
the properties of unitaries. And then,
we're going to go into the issue of
Hamiltonians and how systems change with
time. Systems change with time
by unitary transformation. That's the
message. The unitary operators are the
things which take you from one time step
to another.
And I think we've had enough I've had
enough for tonight.
The preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.